Finding Aid for Eric Stein Papers 1955-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Correspondence
  - 1955-1992
    - T, 1957-1995; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Tallon, Denis, 1961-1971 (Box 14)
    - Taubenfeld, Howard J., 1958-1970 (Box 14)
    - Taylor, Graham, 1976 (Box 14)
    - Tennyson, Leonard B., 1957-1974 (Box 14)
    - Thompson, Dennis, 1964-1980 (Box 14)
    - Thompson, Kenneth W., 1958-1971 (Box 14)
    - Timberg, Sigmund, 1958-1969 (Box 14)
    - Tunc, André, 1961-1965 (Box 14)
    - U, 1960-1972 (Box 14)
    - Ulmer, Eugen, 1957-1972 (Box 14)
    - V, 1957-1995; 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Vallance, William Roy, 1956-1957 (Box 14)
    - Van Dijk, Pieter, 1962-1991; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Vanhaeverbeke, M. Guy, 1968-1969 (Box 14)
    - Van Hecke, George, 1961-1972 (Box 14)
    - Van Hoorn, J., 1958-1976 (Box 14)
    - Van Panhuys, H.F., 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Vogel, Clark (U.S. Atomic Energy Commission), 1956-1958 (Box 14)
    - Vogelaar, M. Theoder, 1960-1973 (Box 14)
    - von der Groeben, Hans, 1960-1977 (Box 14)
    - von Mehren, Arthur, 1958-1971 (Box 14)
    - Von Overbeck, A.E., 1964 (Box 14)
    - W, 1956-1995; 7 folders (Box 15)
    - Waelbroeck, Michel, 1965-1989; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Wainhouse, David W., 1957-1969 (Box 15)
    - Wagenbaur, Rolf, 1977-1980 (Box 15)
    - Walker, Herman, Jr., 1958-1959 (Box 15)
    - Weiler, Joseph, 1978-1993 (Box 15)
    - Weiler, Lawrence, 1977-1979 (Box 15)
    - Weiner, Paul E., 1970 (Box 15)
    - Western European Studies, 1963-1971 (Box 15)
    - Wilcox, Francis O., 1956-1969 (Box 15)
    - Wilkes, Daniel, 1964-1966 (Box 15)
    - Willrich, Mason, 1964-1968 (Box 15)
    - Wilmer, Cutler & Pickering
      - 1990 (Box 15)
      - IBM, 1990 (Box 15)
      - Lufthansa, 1990 (Box 15)
    - Wilson Foundation, 1986 (Box 15)
    - Wohlgemuth, Ernest, 1961-1963 (Box 15)
    - Wortley, B.A., 1959-1963 (Box 15)
    - XYZ, 1956-1983; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Y, 1986-1992 (Box 15)
    - Yntema, Hessel E., 1960-1966 (Box 15)
    - Z, 1984-1996 (Box 15)
    - Zweigert, Konrad, 1956-1977; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1973-2001
    The Correspondence, 1973-2001 subseries (1.8 linear feet) covers the years that Stein was involved with the University of Michigan, from 1973 to 2001, but the materials are not restricted to his University activities. This subseries follows his relationships with individuals and organizations and, is tied to his research and teaching, his travels and visiting professorships in Europe, and some personal matters. Communication with other professionals in the international law field, such as Karl Rychetsky and Ulrich Immenga are located here.
    This series has been organized into one alphabetical series. It includes such general headings as "A, 1996-1999," as well as headings for individuals. However, letters from an individual who is listed in a separate folder may also be found under the general heading. Both incoming and outgoing correspondence can be found here. Also of note is the inclusion of materials in foreign languages. Where found, the materials and the language in which they have been written are noted on the folder.
    - A, 1973; 1996-1999 (Box 19)
      some items in Czech
    - American Association of Law Schools, 1995-1997 (Box 19)
    - American Bar Association, 1994-1996 (Box 19)
    - American Foreign Law Association, 1998-2001 (Box 19)
    - American Journal of Comparative Law, 1996 (Box 19)
    - American Journal of International Law, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - American Journal of International Law, 1996-1999; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1996 (Box 19)
    - Auschwitz Lie, 1987-1989 (Box 19)
    - B, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
      (some items are in French, German, Dutch or Czech)
    - Berlin-Wissenschaftskollegs, 1997-1999 (Box 19)
      (some items in German)
    - Bollinger, Lee, 1996-1998 (Box 19)
    - C, 1996-2001 (Box 19)
    - Committee on Legal Education Exchange with China (CLEEC), 1989; 1991 (Box 19)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - Czecho/Slovakia Book, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - Czecho/Slovakia Book Publicity, 1996-1998 (Box 19)
    - Czecho/Slovakia Trip to Prague, 1995 (Box 19)
    - D, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - E, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - European Economic Community (EEC), 1965 (Box 19)
    - Euro Conference, 1999 (Box 19)
    - European Community Studies Association, 1997-1999 (Box 19)
    - F, 1998-2001 (Box 19)
      (some items are in German)
    - G, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - Gaudet, Michel, 1972-1999 (Box 19)
      (some items are in French)
    - Gordan, Virginia, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
    - H, 1996-1999 (Box 19)
      (some items are in Czech)
    - Haltern, Ulrich, (1996, 1999 (Box 19)
    - Hanzlik, Filip, 1995-1998 (Box 19)
    - Henkin, Louis, 1993; 1997 (Box 19)
    - Humboldt Association of America, 1981; 1997-1999 (Box 19)
    - I, 1995-1999 (Box 19)
      (some items in Czech)
    - Immenga, Ulrich, 1995-1996 (Box 19)
    - J (some items in Czech), 1996-2001 (Box 19)
    - K, 1996-1999; 2001 (Box 19)
      (some items in German and Czech)
    - L, 1996-2001 (Box 20)
    - Law Quad Notes, 1997-1999 (Box 20)
    - Legal Aid of Cambodia, 1996 (Box 20)
    - M, 1996-1999; 2001 (Box 20)
    - N, 1997-1999 (Box 20)
      (some items in Danish)
    - O, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
    - P, 1996-1999; 2001 (Box 20)
    - R, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
      (some items in French and Czech)
    - Reunions-General, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Reunions-International, 1997 (Box 20)
    - Rychetsky, Karl, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 20)
      (some items in French, German or Czech)
    - S, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
      (some items in Czech and German)
    - Students, 1994-1997 (Box 20)
    - Students-Recommendations, 1988-1997 (Box 20)
    - T, 1994-1999 (Box 20)
    - U, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
    - V, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
    - W, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
    - XYZ, 1994-1996 (Box 20)
    - Yourow, Dr. Howard Charles, 1993-1998 (Box 20)
- Courses, 1956-1993
  Courses (0.5 linear feet, 1956-1993) illustrate classes taught by Stein through such materials as syllabi, photocopied casebooks, correspondence, and exam questions. A small addition received in the 20007 accession includes material on several courses taught at the University of Arizona.
  - Commerce, 1988 (Box 16)
  - Economic Legal Seminar, 1956 (Box 16)
  - International Law Course and Seminar, 1955-1958 (Box 16)
  - International Law Seminar--South West Africa, circa 1966 (Box 16)
  - International Regulatory Process, 1974 (Box 16)
  - Interstate and Foreign Commerce in the United States and in the European Community (includes casebook), 1989 (Box 16)
  - Introduction to Law and Institutions of the European Community (given at the University of Arizona), 1992 (Box 16)
  - Judicial Review (given at the Collège d'Europe/College of Europe), 1988 (Box 16)
  - Law of Foreign Trade and Investment
    - 1958-1960 (Box 16)
    - Casebook, 1958-1960; 4 folders (Box 16)
  - European Community Law (University of Arizona), 1993 (Box 22)
  - Interstate & Foreign Commerce in the US and in the EC, 1989; 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Introduction to Law and Institutions of the European Community (University of Arizona), 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Law 687 (University of Arizona), undated (Box 22)
- Topical Files, 1956-1999
  The Topical Files series is organized into two subseries, 1956-1982, and 1981-1999, reflecting the major accession in which the collection was received.
  - 1956-1982
    Materials in the Topical Files, 1956-1982 subseries (1.5 linear feet) relates to Stein's professional activities, including his involvement in international studies programs and committees at the University of Michigan and in conferences around the world, and his research activities. Documented here is his work to establish and maintain an international and comparative legal studies exchange program with the university and legal community in Brussels, Belgium during the 1970s. The program involved both students and faculty; the documents are mainly correspondence. Stein was also instrumental in organizing a conference for the joint European-American Study of the Role of the Judiciary, held in Bellagio, Italy in July 1979. The documents pertaining to the conference are mostly correspondence and contain proposals and responses for the focus of the conference. (The Correspondence series also includes material from the Bellagio conference.) Among the ongoing research projects represented here is Stein's work on disarmament. This series contains one linear foot of his research material, including news clippings, reports and memoranda.
    - Atomic Energy Summer Institute, 1956 (Box 16)
    - Bellagio Conference (July 1979), Joint European-American Study of the Role of the Judiciary
      - General (Box 16)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1982; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Brussels Exchange Program
      - General (Box 16)
      - 1970 (Box 16)
      - 1971 (Box 16)
      - 1972 (Box 16)
      - 1973 (Box 16)
      - 1974 (Box 16)
      - 1975 (Box 16)
      - Student reports, 1975-1978 (Box 16)
    - Conflict Resolution (Center for Research on), 1960-1964 (Box 16)
    - Disarmament
      - Antarctica, 1958-1978 (Box 16)
      - Chemical/Biological Warfare, 1966-1980 (Box 16)
      - China, 1971-1973 (Box 16)
      - Conventional Armaments, 1973-1981 (Box 16)
      - European Zones, 1973-1981 (Box 16)
      - Forums, 1970-1972 (Box 16)
      - General, 1970-1981 (Box 16)
      - Hot Line, 1972-1976 (Box 16)
      - India, 1974 (Box 16)
      - International Atomic Energy Agency, 1958-1971 (Box 16)
      - International Control of Atomic Energy, 1957-1962; undated (Box 16)
      - Law and Disarmament, 1971; undated (Box 17)
      - Moon Treaty, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
      - Napalm, 1972 (Box 17)
      - New Systems, 1978-1981 (Box 17)
      - Non-Proliferation Treaty, 1968-1981 (Box 17)
      - Nuclear Weapons
        - General, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
        - Legality, 1958-1971 (Box 17)
      - Outer Space, 1959-1981 (Box 17)
      - Plowshare and Power, 1971-1974 (Box 17)
      - SALT, 1971-1976; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - SALT II, 1972-1979; undated (Box 17)
      - Seabed, 1970-1976 (Box 17)
      - Test Ban, 1958-1980 (Box 17)
      - USSR, 1973-1981 (Box 17)
      - United States, 1981 (Box 17)
      - Verification Forms, 1964-1981 (Box 17)
      - Weapons Trade, 1976-1978 (Box 17)
      - Zones, 1974-1977 (Box 17)
    - Eastern Regional Conference on European and Atlantic Studies, 1967 (Box 17)
    - Faculty Advisory Committee on International Programs (Box 17)
    - Ford Foundation, Frankfurt-Georgetown Institute for International & Foreign Trade Law, 1961-1964; 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Ford Foundation Grant requests (Eric Stein), 1963-1972 (Box 17)
    - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1962-1963 (Box 17)
    - International Atomic Energy Agency, 1956-1957 (Box 17)
    - International & Comparative Legal Studies
      - Students under consideration, 1978-1980 (Box 17)
      - Visiting scholars, 1969-1974 (Box 17)
    - International Law--General, 1955-1958; undated (Box 17)
    - Law School correspondence
      - Bishop, William W., Jr., 1962-1977 (Box 17)
      - Conard, Alfred, 1965-1977 (Box 17)
    - Michigan Yearbook on International Studies, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Press Releases, 1956-1963 (Box 17)
    - United Nations Secretary General, 1961-1962; undated (Box 17)
    - Vandenberg Lecture Committee (Box 17)
    - Western European Studies (Center for) (Box 17)
  - 1981-1999
    Materials in the Topical Files, 1981-1999 subseries (0.4 linear feet) relate to Stein's professional activities, including his involvement in international studies programs and his research activities. Documented here is his participation in the Committee on Legal Education Exchange in China (CLEEC), the American Society of International Law (ASIL) and his participation in arguing for Attorney-Client privilege in the EEC.
    - The American Society of International Law-Meetings and Agendas, 1999 (Box 22)
    - Attorney-Client Privilege in the EEC
      - Correspondence, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Notes and Related Cases, 1981-1986 (Box 22)
        (some items in French)
    - Committee on Legal Education Exchange with China, (CLEEC), 1983-1991; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Mellon Seminar on Transitional Justice, 1998-1999 (Box 23)
    - Opinions on international Law Between, 1991-1992 (Box 23)
    - Reflective Looks at the New Constitutions, 1991-1995 (Box 23)
- Writings
  The series Writings (1.0 linear feet, 1954-1992) contains some of Stein's books along with correspondence and research materials. The articles and speeches are generally found in their entirety, and are occasionally supplemented by correspondence, programs, or notes. Two books of note Czecho/Slovakia: Ethnic Conflict, Constitutional Fissure, Negotiated Breakup and Thoughts From a Bridge: A Retrospective of Writings on New Europe and American Federalism are heavily documented here, as they are cumulative works of Eric Stein's complete career.
  - American Enterprise in the European Common Market: A Legal Profile, 1960 (Box 18)
    - Budget and Memoranda, 1957-1960 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1960; 3 folders (Box 18)
  - "The 'Auschwitz Lie' in German Courts and Politics,", 1986 (Box 18)
  - "The Authority in Internal Law of International Treaties (Section IV, C1): When is an International Agreement "Self-Executing" in American Law?" (report to the International Academy of Comparative Law), 1962 (Box 18)
  - China and the European Community], circa 1985 (Box 18)
  - "Citizen Access to Judicial Review of Administrative Action in a Transnational and Federal Context" (in the American Journal of International Law, 70), 1976 (Box 18)
  - "Decision-Making in the European Communities" (for the Conference on Decision-Making in International Institutions at the University of Chicago School of Business), 1968 (Box 18)
  - Diplomats, Scientists and Politicians: The United States and the Nuclear Test Ban Negotiations--Correspondence, 1961-1966; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - "The European Community in 1983 A Less Perfect Union?" (in Common Market Law Review, 20), 1983 (Box 18)
  - "The European Steel and Coal Community" (in Columbia Law Review), 1954-1958 (Box 18)
  - "Foreign Affairs in a Modern Constitution,", 1990 (Box 18)
  - Harmonization of European Company Laws: National Reform and Transnational Coordination, 1971 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence and Reviews, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - "International Law in Internal Law: Toward Internationalization of Central-Eastern European Constitutions?", 1994 (Box 18)
    (in The American Journal of International Law, 1993)
  - [International Trade], undated (Box 18)
  - "Interstate and Foreign Commerce in the United States and in the European Community" (casebook), circa 1987; 4 folders (Box 18)
  - [Italian Speech--Arms Control], undated (Box 18)
  - "Legal Problems of Developing Regional Markets" (statement at the Conference on International Law called by the World Community Association at the Yale Law School), 1961 (Box 18)
  - "Musings at the Grave of a Federation,", 1994 (Box 18)
  - "Post-Communist Constitution-Making: Confessions of a Comparatist,", 1992 (Box 18)
  - Reviews, 1974; 1989 (Box 18)
  - Some Implications of Expanding United Nations Membership (Carnegie Project)--Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 18)
  - [Spanish Lectures] (in Spanish), circa 1988 (Box 18)
  - [Speech to the Institute on the Common Market, Duke University], 1972 (Box 18)
  - "Treaty-Based Federalism, A.D. 1979" A Gloss on Covey T. Oliver at the Hague Academy" (in the Pennsylvania Law Review) (Box 18)
  - "Uniformity and Diversity in a Divided-Power System: The United States' Experience,", 1985 (Box 18)
  - Conference on Europe after, 1992; 1991 (Box 23)
  - Czecho/Slovakia
    - Draft, October 1995 (Box 23)
    - Notes and Correspondence, 1996-1998 (Box 23)
  - "Devolution or Deconstruction Czecho-Slovak Style", 1992 (Box 23)
  - "International Integration and Democracy: No Love at First Sight", 2001 (Box 23)
  - "On Living In, and with, Divided-Power Systems: A Reminiscence", 1999 (Box 23)
  - 'On the "Auschwitz Lie"' Responses, 1989-1992 (Box 23)
  - "Out of the Ashes of a Federation, Two New Constitutions", 1997 (Box 23)
  - "Peaceful Separation: A New Virus?", 1996 (Box 23)
  - [Speech in Italian], undated (Box 23)
  - Statement on "Democracy Without a People", 1998 (Box 23)
  - "Thinking About Multiple Transformations and New Constitutional Order", 1996 (Box 23)
  - Thoughts From a Bridge
    - Correspondence and Reviews, 1997-2003 (Box 23)
    - Drafts, 1997-2000; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Printer's Layout, undated (Box 23)
- Czech Constitution, 1990-2002
  The Czech Constitution, 1990-2002 (1.2 linear feet) series documents the creation of the Czech Constitution of 1990 and Eric Stein's contributions. The series contains working drafts of the constitutions, Elster Reports I-III, and meeting materials from three main meetings of the constitutional committee. This is a rich series of materials and showcases the development of a modern democratic constitution echoing many post-Soviet concerns. The collection also contains constitutional drafts from Václav Havel and the Civic Forum.
  - Civic Forum-First Draft of the New Constitution, 1990 (Box 20)
  - Constitution of the Czech Republic-First Working Draft, 1990 (Box 20)
  - Constitution of the Slovak Republic-First Working Draft, 1990 (Box 20)
    (some items in Slovak)
  - Constitutional Working File (Federal Allocation), 1990-1991 (Box 20)
  - "Czech and Slovak Constitutional Amendments on Foreign Affairs", Speech on, March 6, 2002; 2002 (Box 21)
    (some items in Czech and/or Slovak)
  - Draft Constitution of the Slovak Republic (given in Bratislava), 1991 (Box 21)
  - Elster Report I, Czech Court -- Legal Reports, 1990 (Box 21)
  - Elster Report II, Current Constitution, 1990 (Box 21)
  - Elster Report III, Drafts of Complete Constitutions (some items in Czech), 1990 (Box 21)
  - Emergency Action, 1990-1991 (Box 21)
  - Havel Drafts of the New Constitution, 1990-1992; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Meetings
    - First Meeting, undated (Box 21)
    - Second Meeting in Salzburg and Prague, 1990-1991 (Box 21)
    - Second Meeting -- Resultant Papers, 1990 (Box 21)
    - Third Meeting in Bratislava and Prague, 1991 (Box 21)
  - New Constitution Legislation, 1991-1992 (Box 21)
  - New Slovak Constitution Legislation, 1992-1994 (Box 21)
  - Notes on Czech Articles and Notes After Conversation with Schwartz, undated (Box 21)
  - On the Constitutional Courts, 1990-1993 (Box 21)
  - On the Old Czechoslovakian Constitution, undated (Box 21)
  - Reaction to the New Constitutions, 1992 (Box 21)
    (some items in Czech and /or Slovak)